ice cream and gelato what is the
difference
gelato these days is a term that's
thrown around really really loosely it's
very fashionable to sell and make gelato
but obviously italians have been doing
it for
ever basically so what actually is
gelato
[Music]
gelato is ice cream that is lower in fat
and higher in sugars it's actually
served at a slightly higher temperature
as well has less overrun and a little
bit more chew to it
[Music]
ice cream on the other hand is higher in
fat
slightly lower in sugar has more overrun
and doesn't have that dense texture
stabilizers are used in gelato a lot
these days to recreate that creamy mouth
mouthfeel that ice cream would
ordinarily give you
now there's a whole thing about egg
yolks for gelato i'm not gelato expert i
don't really know that much about it but
some people will say that originally it
did or didn't use egg yolks there seems
to be a mix of recipes around the world
so make whatever suits yourself
if you're unsure an egg yolk here or
there is a really good emulsifier just
to bring all your ingredients your fat
and waters together so what we're going
to do today is we're going to make a bit
of both scoop them up and compare the
two
and what better way than to try another
flavor or another type of coffee is this
we're gonna try uh sakura coffee
grounds so
everything came from japan that i'm
wearing today we're gonna make some of
this and we're gonna make coffee ice
cream and coffee gelato using this
sakura coffee itself
[Music]
[Applause]
as discussed we're going to make the
sakura coffee and gelato first thing we
need to do though is take all of the
milk required for both these recipes
and get those coffee grinds sat in there
and steeping for a good few hours all
the amounts are in the description below
so you can follow both these recipes
exactly if you want to do that
slowly mix in your coffee grounds until
they're really well incorporated and
that milk is nice and warm and then just
leave it ticking over on the lowest
possible heat for at least half an hour
that enables a really nice strong coffee
flavor to infuse into that milk when
that time's up turn the heat off and
then strain the milk through a
cheesecloth you will lose some of the
milk i lost about 10 here still sat in
the coffee grounds you can just top the
amount back up so we're going to start
with the gelato first take your coffee
infused milk and put that back in a pan
at that stage add your sugars
your egg yolks
give them a good whisk
and then add your milk powder slowly
bring the mix up to temperature whisking
consistently
we've brought this up to 60 to 65
degrees centigrade just to make sure
that the egg yolks cooked we use
pasteurized eggs here so actually don't
need to do this but
it's good practice either way when
that's done take it off the heat add it
into your container at that stage add in
your 120mls worth of cream we've used
whipping cream here and then put it in
the fridge to chill down the next stage
is the ice cream version it's exactly
the same process as you did for the
gelato but the numbers are different so
you can add in your coffee infused milk
add in your sugars your egg yolks and
your skim milk powder again bring it up
to 60 65 degrees c
take it off the heat add it to your
container and then finally chill it down
with the cream here and then put it in
the fridge again to chill down
completely
when both mixes are chilled take them
out the fridge one at a time and churn
them the time will depend on the machine
that you have but both these took less
than 10 minutes for mine whilst your ice
cream's churning it it's a good time to
mention that we're going to do the next
episode in our chocolate series next
week we're actually going to make bloody
chocolate ice cream there's going to be
a lot of chocolate ice cream made here
and we're going to discuss the ins and
outs and whys so make sure you like and
subscribe so you don't miss out
when they're ready load them into a tub
and put them in the freezer for at least
a few hours okie doke
so
gelato
ice cream both made from
this sakura coffee
let's get some scooped up onto the plate
and try each one
[Music]
here we go
gelato
ice cream
start with
[Music]
very familiar texture
very creamy
lasting flavor still going still going
i make my ice cream slightly higher fat
than some people do
i find it makes the taste linger even
longer
gelato technically the taste will end
sooner because there's much lower fat
but let's dig into this one now
[Music]
less overrun denser ice cream a little
bit of a chew to it not too bad
now that is distinctly the difference
something that a lot of home ice cream
makers will struggle with is actually
making ice cream because ice cream
should have a certain amount of overrun
the ice cream you buy in the stores can
have anything up to a hundred percent
overrun so that means if you put in one
liters worth of mix you can get two
liters worth of ice cream out of it
any more than that it's technically
illegal to sell it as ice cream but it
will be labeled as something like a
frozen dessert
now in england
there are no rules or laws
as to what you can call anything we've
seen gelato in england
uh 15 to 18
fat with 25 sugars we've also seen it
where the overrun is obviously 75 based
on weight
you can call it what you like but in
certain parts of the world specifically
italy there are laws regarding gelato
and ice cream and the difference if you
have a home ice cream machine
you are likely going to create some kind
of mix in between the two you're
unlikely to achieve the higher overrun
required for ice cream
but you also won't achieve the same kind
of texture and consistency required for
gelato because you're using an ice cream
recipe so actually you're going to
create a frankenstein kind of mix of the
two
but that is sometimes why your home ice
cream or often your home ice cream
tastes much nicer than the stuff you buy
in the stores because it's creamier it's
denser you've got that creaminess high
fat content of the ice cream but with
the denseness of gelato somewhere in
between
so that is technically the difference
between ice cream and gelato ice cream
higher overrun
higher fat slightly lower sugar
gelato lower fat
slightly higher sugar
much less overrun one final thing to
mention is that gelato is technically
churned slower than ice cream as well
and that gives you that denser low
overrun final product
so
it doesn't really make any difference
they both taste just as good as each
other if you're
if you're on a low fat kind of diet
gelato is probably better for you you
are getting more sugar in there as well
so take that into account but
anyway i hope you enjoyed this video
just a slight touch on the difference
between ice cream and gelato i'm gonna
sit here and eat all of this probably
gonna make some of this have massive
caffeine overload and get working on the
next chocolate
ice cream episode so if you don't want
to miss that make sure you like and
subscribe and we'll see you next week
[Music]
you